<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from the Marquesse of Worcester to the committee of Parliament sitting in the county of Monmouth, concerning his sons landing with Irish forces: and the committees answer thereunto. Ordered by the Commons assembled in Parliament, that this letter and answer be forthwith printed and published. H. Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
            <author>Worcester, Henry Somerset, Marquis of, 1577-1646.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96910</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3536</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E340_11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200875</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861500</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861500</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113637</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96910)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113637)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 55:E340[11])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from the Marquesse of Worcester to the committee of Parliament sitting in the county of Monmouth, concerning his sons landing with Irish forces: and the committees answer thereunto. Ordered by the Commons assembled in Parliament, that this letter and answer be forthwith printed and published. H. Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</title>
                  <author>Worcester, Henry Somerset, Marquis of, 1577-1646.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edw. Husband, printer to the Honorable House of Commons,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Iune 9. 1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The Marquis of Worcester's letter is dated Raglan, May 29. 1646.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Raglan Castle (Raglan, Monmouthshire) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113637:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> A LETTER FROM The Marqueſſe of <hi>Worceſter</hi> TO The Committee of Parliament ſitting in the County of MONMOUTH, Concerning His Sons landing with Iriſh Forces: AND The Committees Anſwer thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="order_to_print">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ORdered by the Commons aſſembled in Parliament, That this Letter and Anſwer be forthwith Printed and Publiſhed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>H: Elſynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>London, Printed for <hi>Edw. Husband,</hi> Printer to the Honorable Houſe of Commons, <hi>Iune</hi> 9, 1646.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:113637:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:113637:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Governour of</hi> Chepſtow, <hi>and the reſt of the Committee for the Parliament for the County of Monmouth.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving notice that you are not ignorant of my Sons being landed with the <hi>Iriſh</hi> For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I am ſo much a father and tenderer of the whole Countreys Ruine and Deſtruction, that if their coming hither be upon the return of yours occaſioned to be haſtened, you, and not I, muſt be the occaſion of the ſame, who the whole Countrey will have juſt cauſe to curſe. <hi>I</hi> am not able to ſubſiſt without my Rents and Living, which you have
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113637:3"/> taken all from me; if you pleaſe to give me undelayed Reparations therein, I ſhall be glad to have occaſion to live a quiet Neighbor amongſt you: if other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, it ſhall be evident to the whole world, that you force me to what mine own nature hath no liking of, and yet no other then the Word of God and the Law of Nature doth warrant and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. Thus, expecting your Anſwer by this Meſſenger, <hi>I</hi> reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>As you give occaſion,</hi> H: Worceſter.</signed>
               <dateline>Raglan, <date>May 29. 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:113637:3"/>
            <head>The Committees Anſwer.</head>
            <p>VVEe received your Lordſhips Letter by a Drum: your Sons landing with Iriſh, and your other Sons News of the Kings being in the head of a great Army, are pretty Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitical inventions to uphold your Souldiers ſpirits, but cannot diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage us in proſecution of our juſt cauſe: VVe ſee not how the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over ſuch bloody Iriſh Rebels, agreeth with vvhat your Lordſhip would be eſteemed, a Father of your Country; we believe ſo unnatural a one can hardly be paralleld, and in charity to your Lordſhip ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113637:4"/> imprecations of curſes on the Author of our miſeries, leaſt wee thereby adde a greater weight to your ſcore; you know whom to blame for want of Rent; your fatherſhip of the Countreys Ruine, hath been the cauſe of depriving both your ſelf and us from enjoying our own; and had your Lordſhips will and good nature accepted what was about ſix moneths ago reſpectfully offered, this poor County had not now ſo groaned un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Burthen of VVar: For your Lordſhips undelayed Reparation, we muſt try your patience by a little fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſideration; your vvarrant from the VVord of God or Law of Nature for your actions we finde not, unleſſe <hi>Raglan</hi> bee our <hi>Antipodes,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:113637:4"/> where the Rule is oppoſition to <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains</hi> true Bible and Nature; we ſhall leave your Lordſhip to your own good Inclinations, and in requital of News, and for your Lordſhips better information, have ſent you His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties and the Scots Declarations, not deſiring further to trouble you, but hope we may have occaſion to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe our ſelves</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips Friends and Servants,
<list>
                     <item>Roger Williams,</item>
                     <item>Thomas Hughs,</item>
                     <item>Henry Herbert,</item>
                     <item>William Herbert,</item>
                     <item>Rice Williams,</item>
                     <item>Chr: Katchmey,</item>
                     <item>William Blethyn,</item>
                     <item>Edward Morgan.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
